<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prelatical church-man against the phanatical Kirk-man, or, A vindication of the author of The sufferings of the Church of Scotland</title>
            <author>Author of The sufferings of the Church of Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11966623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11966623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51731</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51731)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 820:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prelatical church-man against the phanatical Kirk-man, or, A vindication of the author of The sufferings of the Church of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Author of The sufferings of the Church of Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>A reply to Animadversions on the sufferings of the Church of Scotland. cf. p. 2.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51731:1"/>
            <p>THE PRELATICAL CHURCH-MAN, Againſt the <hi>Phanatical Kirk-Man,</hi> OR, A VINDICATION OF THE AUTHOR OF THE SUFFERINGS OF THE Church of Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51731:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THO I have always had an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to Writing: And thought it greater Prudence in a Man meanly gifted, to be ſilent and conceal his Weakneſs, than in Print to publiſh and proclaim it: Yet when the Credit of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> lies at <hi>Stake;</hi> and that of <hi>England,</hi> whereof I am a <hi>Member,</hi> is reflected on, I thought in Conſcience I was bound; and that in Duty to my <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers</hi> I could do no loſs, than to confute thoſe Things, which I know to be <hi>Aſperſions;</hi> and to proceed from a <hi>Paraſite,</hi> who tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſes and ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erts the <hi>Truth.</hi> He has lately wrote a little <hi>Pamphale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> called, <hi>Animadverſions on the Sufferings of the Church of</hi> Scotland: Which indeed is ſo full of <hi>Venom,</hi> and of Words ſo unbecoming a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> That one would think this <hi>Author</hi> was ſome <hi>Amphibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Creature,</hi> void of all <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>Religion:</hi> I'm inform'd he's a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> or rather a <hi>Salamanca Doctor;</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for ſome time beat his <hi>Brains,</hi> and crack'd his <hi>Scull,</hi> in the Study of the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law</hi> (which he could never Reach nor Comprehend) did at laſt, expecting ſome Relief from <hi>Phyſick,</hi> read <hi>Culpep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi>'s Midwifry, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Problems, and <hi>Burton</hi>'s Melancholy: And then, after the Faſhion of our <hi>Quacks,</hi> ſet up for an eminent <hi>Doctor:</hi> But had he been a <hi>Civilian,</hi> I ſhould have expected <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> from him: Or if a <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> ſomething to <hi>heal,</hi> and not to <hi>feſter</hi> our <hi>Sores:</hi> But what he ſcribles being mere <hi>Stuff</hi> and <hi>Traſh,</hi> and obſcene ſcurilous <hi>Language,</hi> I ſhould rather fancy him to be of Kin to the <hi>Billingſgate-Wenches,</hi> whom, I think, he more by half reſembles than our <hi>Biſhops do Antichriſt, or our Church the Hirarchy of</hi> Rome: or by his Words, <hi>Helliſh Prelates and Infernal Furies,</hi> one would take him to be a <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronian Phanatical Thunderer,</hi> whoſe Excellency conſiſts in ſomeing out <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Hell,</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> in his <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit:</hi> A Subject ſo common to this <hi>Sect,</hi> That he who preaches <hi>Salvation,</hi> or <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Redemption,</hi> is excommunicated by 'em: But I think I need give no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Character</hi> of our <hi>Author,</hi> his mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ugly, and deform'd <hi>Iſſue.</hi> His <hi>Animadverſions</hi> ſhewing him to be a Malicious and Envious <hi>Perſon;</hi> whoſe Bowels are fall of <hi>Gall,</hi> and his Tongue dip'd in <hi>Poiſon:</hi> For he ſhews ſo much ill Nature in every <hi>Paragraph</hi> he writes, that one would take him to be an <hi>Enemy</hi> to the Race of <hi>Mankind:</hi> And indeed he is ſo full of <hi>Choler,</hi> and ſo hurried with <hi>Paſſion,</hi> that he lets his Words fly at Random, without Reaſon, Deliberation, or Senſe: And this being the hot and firy Temper of our <hi>Phanatical Zealot,</hi> I hope the Ingenious <hi>Reader</hi> will be pleaſed to examine what this <hi>Kirk Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> ſays.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51731:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Scotch Animadverſions</hi> CONFUTED.</head>
            <p>IF <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was not of Divine Right, which very Eminent and Learned Divines have aſſerted: Yet being of Apoſtolical Conſtitution, according to the received Opinion of the moſt Judicious, Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Writers, being eſtabliſhed by poſitive Laws in a Nation: And by all unbyaſſed and unprejudiced Perſons being acknowledged the beſt of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical</hi> Governments. I ſhould think it no <hi>ſuperlaive Impudence</hi> in one of this Perſwaſion to diſown all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious <hi>Meetings</hi> and <hi>Conventicles</hi> for their Church: Nor do I think it any piece of Arrogance in the Biſhops, or the Prieſts, of this Church, nor in any of their Communion, to aſſume to themſelves the Name of a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church: And tho' our Ingenious <hi>Obſervat.</hi> in the firſt Page of his Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, compares the National Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to that Univerſal Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and appears to make no diſtinction between the Two, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Scotch</hi> by way of Similitude and Compariſon. Yet he is much miſtaken in his Logick, and if he had not told us he was an Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Man, I ſhould have thought that he was Bred at <hi>Greſham-College,</hi> or as the Phraſe is in his own Idiom, in the College of <hi>Buckhaven;</hi> for here he makes no diſtinction between the whole, and its parts, and appears as little to diſcern, whether <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Species</hi> be the ſame; for the <hi>Scotch</hi> owning their Church, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l other Churches, to be but a Number of Men ſet apart, or collected together, to Worſhip God after that Form pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd in his Word: They own <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and all the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Believers, that Worſhip in a Decent Form, to be a Church as well as themſelves, nor did they ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51731:3"/> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> from being a Church, <hi>tho' in their Pulpits, and in their Books, they have all diſown'd it for a True and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> To that here our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadvertor, either underſtands not what an Univerſal Church is, or if he does, is very unjuſt in impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a Church what ſhe never thought nor did: For there being but one True Church in the World, and all National Churches being Members of this one, that which comprehends all, muſt only be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and none but our Author could be ſo Ignorant as to think there was two Univerſals of the ſame kind; or that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> did ever in Diſcipline, or Doctrine, ſhake Hands with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as our worthy Animadverſioniſt, with a ſtock of Confidence and Ignorance does Aſſert.</p>
            <p>But as Malice will make a Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, where there is no ſubject, and Aſperſe, where there is no Blemiſh; ſo likewiſe this Worthy Gentleman would make the World believe, that there was nothing like Devotion and Piety among the Biſhops and Prieſts of this Church. Nay, that they were ſo Wicked in their Lives and Converſations, that they did Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Encourage the worſt and greateſt of Crimes. This certainly muſt be a Notorious Falſhood, for I my ſelf, during Twelve or Thirteen Years, have been a conſtant Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Lives and Carriage of the Clergy; and in all that time could never ſee, nor ſo much as hear, of any that was guilty of the leaſt Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanor. I Liv'd at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> where they were every Day to be ſeen, and happen'd to converſe with thoſe who would have made a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of a Mole-hill, and made any little-Failing, or Infirmity, in a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the moſt Heionus and Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating Crime; yet notwithſtanding their envious and watchful Eyes which did follow and attend the Biſhops even to their Homes, yet could I never hear of any Scandalous thing laid to their Charge; nay, I never heard of any Biſhop but Dr. <hi>Paterſon,</hi> late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> that ever was tax'd with any thing undecent, or unbecoming, their Gown; and it was the Opinion of moſt Men, that the Report rais'd on him was very Falſe, and did meerly proceed from Envy. Becauſe the Duke of <hi>Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> did take ſo much notice of him; therefore they thought, the only way to be even with the Biſhop and the Duke, was to call the Biſhop his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hatton</hi>'s Gallant, which I dare affirm, is a Notorious Lie; and 'tis pity that <hi>Scandalum Magnatum</hi> does not reach as well there, this foul Mouth'd Wretch, as it ſhould have done if it had been ſpoken here. But was it all true he alledges of this Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and of the Miniſter of <hi>Libber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town,</hi> his Names-ſake, yet is it not Nonſenſe in any Man to ſay, that <hi>Vitium Perſonae,</hi> is <hi>Vitium Regiminis,</hi> or that a Company of Men, and that Office and Dignity they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with, ſhould ſuffer, becauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51731:3"/> ſome particular Member of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety does miſcarry and tranſgreſs. Had I thus retorted his Anſwer, and told him, That all the Presbyterian Miniſters are Rogues, becauſe <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſon</hi> their late Repreſentative was ſuch, in Deflowring a Ladies Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, under whoſe Roof he Lodg'd; certainly the <hi>Obſervator</hi> would be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and yet it is no more than what he himſelf has done to render <hi>quid pro quo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But paſſing by this, I ſay, that the <hi>Scotch</hi> Biſhops were Men of Good Lives; and if from External Actions we may be allowed to call Men Pious and Good, they were certainly ſuch; for they were Charitable to the Poor, Courteous and Kind to the Stranger, did Relieve the Widow and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, and Perſons of all Ranks and Qualities had an eaſie Acceſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: In their Doctrine they were Orthodox, in their Diſcourſe very Modeſt and Grave, and in their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to all very Humble and <hi>Meek;</hi> all which I Appeal to the Author's Conſcience, whether, or not, theſe following Men were ſuch, Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> Dr. <hi>Young</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> Dr. <hi>Laury</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Brechin,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Atkins</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Galloway;</hi> and as to the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Clergy, was not <hi>Mr. Lundy,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Meldrum,</hi> the Miniſters of the <hi>Toll Booth-Church,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cant</hi> of the <hi>New,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Scot</hi> of the <hi>Abbey,</hi> and all the others of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> Men of Piety and Learning, which if he ſhould deny, many Thouſands will contractict him to his Face, and this may ſerve to Anſwer all alledged in the Firſt, Second, and Third Pages.</p>
            <p>But as our <hi>Obſervator</hi> Upbraids the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo he likewiſe muſt have a ſling at <hi>England,</hi> and tho' it be the beſt Conſtituted Church in the World, and that which certainly comes nigheſt to the Primitive times, yet that part of it which was to wait on her <hi>Royal Highneſs</hi> the Princeſs <hi>Anne,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is Calumniated and Revil'd, as if they had been a Sect of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> who thought Luxury and Uncleanneſs to be no Sin. Thus he has the Impudence to ſay, <hi>That the Chappel was a Bawdy-Houſe, and all the Members of their Church guilty of Fornication and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Sure if there was any ſuch thing, it was among thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who could, when the Duke of <hi>York</hi> was there, have a Pardon for any Sin. But for the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I did not hear any thing of them, and tho' I will not Juſtifie what is Wicked or Criminal in them, yet this I can ſay, that I never ſee any Hearers more Attentive, or a Prieſt Adminiſter, or People Receive the Sacrament, with greater Piety, Gravity, and Decency, then all of this Church did, when the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> was then at <hi>Edenburgh:</hi> And thus to Abuſe a Prelate of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, I mean, the Reverend Dr. <hi>Turner,</hi> who was ever lookd upon to be a Man of a Good Life; and to Reflect on a Princeſs of the Royal Blood, is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51731:4"/> a Crime methinks which deſerves the Pillory at leaſt.</p>
            <p>In the 7th. and 8th. Pages he tells us of the diligence of the <hi>Presbyterian Parſons,</hi> and of ſending <hi>Lay-Elders to ſee whether Maſters of Families do Pray,</hi> this may be, and I know it was <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>'s principle, <hi>quoties vis fallere plebem finge Deum:</hi> and the Cuſtom of the falſe Apoſtles (who would have St. <hi>Paul</hi> and others differing from themſelves, to be thought Men of diſſolute Lives) to pretend to a Strictneſs of Life and Converſation, which the Goſpel did not enjoin, and as for theſe meaſures they now take, we have known the like to have been done by Major <hi>Wear,</hi> who was Guilty of <hi>Sodomy, Buggery</hi> and <hi>Inceſt,</hi> and by a <hi>Phanatical</hi> Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Mitchael,</hi> who taking aim to kill the A.B. <hi>Sharp;</hi> Shot Biſhop <hi>Honiwood</hi> through the hand, and it is no new thing for us to know that this Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Tribe will devour Widows hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and for a pretence make long Prayers. He would alſo have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they neither <hi>Swear</hi> nor <hi>Drink;</hi> that may be, but I am ſure, <hi>Cheat</hi> and <hi>Lie,</hi> Confoundedly they will: and Pray and Exclaim againſt their Governours as the aforeſaid <hi>Mitchael</hi> did, for he twenty times ſaid he had no deſign againſt the Arch-Biſhop, and afterwards confeſs'd his Crime to the Lord Chancellour: and I my ſelf ſaw <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kid,</hi> 2. <hi>Ph. Miniſters</hi> Hang'd for Preaching Rebellion, and when they were on the Scaffold there was a Pardon offer'd 'em to Pray for the King, and they would not; and I heard <hi>Cameron</hi> once in My Lady <hi>Bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons, Pray for the Confuſion of the King and his Council,</hi> and yet our <hi>Obſ.</hi> would make theſe <hi>Persbyterians</hi> to be for Monarchy; Who have ever been Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Crown'd heads: Let 'em talk what they will, he who hates a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> can never love a <hi>King.</hi> And he who treads on a Mitre, will quickly pull off the Crown, ſo that ſtill the Maxim will prove true, no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But next the <hi>Obſer.</hi> according to his wonted Cruelty, would have the Chuch of <hi>England</hi> believe that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> differs from her, thereby endeavouring to obſtruct their Charity, and farther <hi>alledges, that the Aſſemblies Confeſſion of Faith was taught at</hi> Edenburgh. Which is ſo falſe, that when I my ſelf was there, which was much about the time he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions nine or ten years ago, there was not any of the Tutors taught it: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his own, who was then reputed a Man of little Senſe, and a <hi>Phanatick</hi> of the firſt Magnitude, I mean <hi>Mr. Pillans,</hi> who was often hiſs'd at in our publick Examinations, and made a ſubject of Scoff and Deriſion for all. But beſides the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy ſince ever I could remember, has been ſtill hugg'd and admir'd by the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> party, and though they did not dare publickly to profeſs it, becauſe of the Furious and Inſolent Rabble, yet there was Arch-Biſhop <hi>Burnet,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Atkins,</hi> and ſeveral others of our Biſhops, who have had it read in their Families, and the Sacrament given to many of the Clergy together, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51731:4"/> many of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> party were ſo glad when they ſaw this Service counti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd by Authority in the Abby, that they came thither in Crouds, all which I refer to the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Ely;</hi> and the great reſpect they always ſhew the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, in their own Country puts this beyond all diſpute.</p>
            <p>In the 14th. and ſome of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding pages, he makes a Catalogue of the <hi>Persbyterians</hi> Sufferings, and by what I can underſtand, thinks it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable to deal Juſt ſo by the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Party, but I thought this pretender to Religion had not ſo learned Chriſt, as to tell us, that the law of <hi>Retalliation</hi> is ſtill in force; but if it was, which I ſuppoſe in all Particulars no Man will aſſert, if it be not a <hi>Phanatick:</hi> Yet I think the <hi>Epiſcopalians,</hi> as he calls 'em, deſerve no ſuch Uſage; becauſe the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> were guilty every Day of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> did make many Uproars and Inſurrections, and did ſeveral times involve the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Blood; and to ſubdue and quell ſuch Spirits, and to puniſh ſuch great Offenders, who did diſturb the Peace and Government of the Nation, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks could be no Crime at all; and their Sufferings being for doing Ill, they ſhould be aſham'd to glory in them, or to think, that by turns they ought to puniſh the Church.</p>
            <p>And as to <hi>the Sufferings of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Church,</hi> which he ſo confidently contradicts, and ſays, That the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor cannot inſtance the <hi>Perſons, Place, and time:</hi> He walks upon a falſe Suppoſition, for there was a Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not many Days ago, with me upon the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> who came from <hi>Galloway</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who ſaid, That he would ſwear it before the King and Council, and prove it by ſeveral Witneſſes, that all was true that that Ingenious and Charitable Gentleman wrote, and that there was much more true than what was there contained; and if there ſhould be any Occaſion for it, he would prove both the Time and Place. Nay, I myſelf do remember, That Six or Seven Years ago there was one Mr. <hi>Kirk,</hi> a Miniſter in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> who told me that theſe <hi>Phanaticks</hi> were ſo furious, that they did firſt Rob a neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſter of his Goods, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did pull down the Houſe upon him. And if they did commit ſuch Outrages and Villanies when the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government was in force, what leſs than Barbarity could be expected, when every <hi>Phanatick</hi> was allowed to do what was right in his own Eyes. And this verefies that Epithet which the Revered Biſhop <hi>Atkins</hi> bid a Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Signet give him, John <hi>or</hi> William <hi>by the Indignation of God Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Incarnate Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe are the men who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the murthering of their <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> a Crime having ſuch a Train of aggravating Circumſtances, that none but a <hi>Phanatick,</hi> without Horror and Trembling would mention it: For this poor Gentleman, being gray head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and above Eighty Years old, was in his Coach beſet by a Company of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51731:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Phanaticks;</hi> and tho his Daughter, with Tears in her Eyes, pray'd 'em, for Chriſt's ſake, to ſpare her aged Father; and he himſelf had earneſtly entreated them, after they had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to butcher him, to let him have but time to recommend his Soul to God; they in the very inſtant of Prayer cut off his Right Hand, ſhot him through the Body, and left him in the Choach wallowing in his Blood, which made his Daughter miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, and being Melancholy, was in great Danger; of loſing her Life: Yet this worthy good man does this <hi>Cannibal</hi> exclaim againſt, and tho Death ſhould put an end to the Rage of the worſt of Men, yet could this vile Wretch be contented to be glutted with his Blood again. And his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice does not terminate here, but he muſt likewiſe have a Stroke at the Metropolitans and Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> and compares them to <hi>Titus Oates,</hi> and calls 'em <hi>Dark Lanthorns,</hi> who are the great Lights of our Church, and have done more Good in one Week, than he and all the <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctors can do in a whole Age: And tho our Author be ſo favourable to <hi>Oates,</hi> yet I think it not ſtrange, ſince <hi>Birds of a Feather will flock toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Beſides this, he threatens, That if any of 'em ſhould read the Service, or endeavour to introduce it to <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they may perhaps ſuffer as much as Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> did, that is, become a Victim and Sacrifice to the People, which one Expreſſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a Rope, if there was no other; and 'tis pity ſuch an Incendiary ſhould be ſuffered to live: Yet I would, with all my Heart, that there was no greater Danger than this, and that <hi>Ireland</hi> was as eaſily ſubdued, as <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> might again be brought in and kept in <hi>Scotland:</hi> And I am ſure, was there a Pole about <hi>Eipiſcopacy</hi> there, that Three Parts in Four of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would be for it; and all of 'em in a few Years might, perhaps, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to entertain the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Which, if they cannot as yet be ſo happy as to enjoy, I ſhall earneſtly pray to God, That he would make their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> ſucceſsful in their Arms, That he would give them the Necks of their Enemies, bleſs 'em with a happy and proſperous Reign, and make them yet inſtrumental in re-eſtabliſhing that <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> which in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by a Trick was Voted out. That all good men may with the Poet ſay,</p>
            <q>There is a Church, but not a Kirk of <hi>Scots.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
